(Cara) Good afternoon everyone
and welcome to Smart Company’s first webinar of the year
which is “How to Deal With Customers Who Won’t Pay”
which I think you'll agree is a pretty important topic for all SME’s
My name is Cara Waters. I’m the editor of Smart Company
and today I’m joined with- virtually, because they are in different place to me,
but, Andrew Baird who is a principal in Accounting and Business Advisory at WHK
and Emily Jaksch whose title is
Head Guru at HR Gurus.
So for the webinar, if you haven’t logged into one of these before,
just to let you know the way to participate is, firstly by listening.
The audio will automatically be streamed through your computer speakers,
and another way is via Twitter.
So you can use the @SmartCompany or the #smartcowebinar.
Now, the major way though if you want to get really interactive
is to ask questions via the questions pane, which is,
you’ll see on your computer screen.
What you do is you type in your questions
in the space at bottom and click on send.
I’ll then be asking our two presenters
Andrew and Emily all your queries.
So, I really encourage you to send them through because it is an,
important topic and something
that I’m sure a lot of you do have questions about.
And, also, I'd just like to thank our partners for today’s webinar,
who are, which is Business Victoria,
providing Big Help for Small Business.
And one final reminder before I hand over to Andrew and Emily is that,
you don’t have to worry about furiously copying down notes
because we will send you copy of the slides to the webinar
and recording of the webinar as well.
So, you can relax a little bit.
or feel free to take notes if you want to.
So, I'll now hand over and to let them introduce
themselves properly, to Andrew and Emily.
(Andrew) Great. Thanks Cara. My name is Andrew Baird.
I'm a principal with WHK Accountants and Advisors, and we specialise in providing accounting and advisory services to the SME market.
(Emily) And my name is Emily Jaksch and I'm also with the SME market and run a HR consultancy.
(Andrew) And today, Emily and I are going to be talking to you about
how we deal with customers who won't pay. And it's all the key areas we're going to cover off today.
First of all we're going to be talking about key cashflow issues,
that affect businesses.
How to avoid common cashflow mistakes, and tips for preventing customers
becoming late payers, and ways to deal with late paying customers.
And as Cara said in the introduction please, we're more than happy to
take questions throughout the presentation as we go along.
So make sure you get tapping as topics that come up or questions come up.
Emily and I, we're more than happy to take those questions from you throughout the presentation.
So, really quickly, there's so many causes of cashflow issues, in business.
Unplanned capital purchases, debtors not paying, not managing your stock,
over spending, lack of systems and processes, too much bank debt,
inefficient operations, poor planning, poor record keeping,
and not managing the creditors properly.
The list could go on and on.
Em, as a business owner, what are some of the things that
you've experienced that have been key causes of cash flow issues, and financials.
(Emily) I guess the key to issue is not having a process.
If you don't focus on it everyday, it just kind of gets away from you.
So that's probably the biggest thing I have learnt
as a small business owner, is that you need to have a clear process,
a good invoicing process, good relationships, and that you follow that through.
(Andrew) Yes, so a far bit of planning involved in keeping on top of cashflow?
(Emily) Yes, definitely.
(Andrew) Yeah.
And so as a business which provides services to other SME's and large corporates,
so would debtors be a key issue for you?
(Emily) It is a big issue for us. We've got our debtor day down to 14 days, which is really good,
but that's only because we're on top of it every single day. I used to have a manual spreadsheet that I would use.
Now I use Xerox which is really good.
Its automated the whole process, so there's no double entry involved.
Now, we veered away from that, it's been really good for our cash flow.
(Andrew) Yeah. So, if we just move on, even I,
we could get top three causes of cash flow issues in small businesses.
It's really poor debtor management, lack of planning, and poor record keeping.
Those are what we see, and it's certainly what you've experienced
(Emily) Sure definitely.
(Andrew) So, moving now, how to avoid...
(Cara) Andrew and Emily, sorry, sorry to interrupt there.
We're just getting feedback,
people are having trouble listening to you.
Are you able to speak into the microphone as we were, as we were doing before?
Apologies everyone.
(Andrew) That's okay, let's see how we go now.
So, let's talk about how we can...
(Cara) It's better from my end. So, yes, we're getting confirmation.
People are preferring that.
And Emily as well, when it's your turn,
if you just speak, speak better, more clearly into the microphone.
Thank you.
(Andrew) Sorry. So, let's have a chat Em
about how we can avoid some of these cashflow mistakes.
Some of the things and the tips that we've come up with here are
making sure there's clear roles and responsibilities in the business,
good stock management, good reporting, regular cash flow forecasting,
refinancing early, customer selections, choosing your customers,
having a really good systems and processes around debtor management.
Real-time information, Em, you mentioned before that you were using spreadsheets to manage your business.
(Emily) Yeah.
(Andrew) And, so, tell us a little bit about that
and what prompted you to move to Xerox.
(Emily) Sure. So, initially, I was using a spreadsheet to look at when people pay.
If they haven't paid me, if the invoices were overdue, I would start going through a processing of emailing them,
and calling them, which was a lot of work because you had to switch between your bank statement,
or online banking and the spreadsheet, which didn't make sense at all.
And then my accountant introduced me to Xerox,
which is a fantastic tool because it gives you real-time information because it links through to your bank statement.
So, you can very easily see who hasn't paid,
and everyday you can be on top of it, which is really important in my reports.
On debtor day, you have a really good idea of who your offenders are, which is also really helpful.
(Andrew) So, you can do all your invoicing through Xerox and you automatically,
(Emily) Yep,
(Andrew) you can see without having to go to the bank who's paid and who hasn't.
(Emily) Exactly. It's like, so everyday you reconcile your account.
Through the link to your bank statement so you can see
what money is going out, coming in, and whether it's overdue.
You can also send follow up invoices through that system to the people who aren't paying.
(Andrew) So, it really makes cash flow management, and cash flow planning,
and debtors really front line, is that..?
(Emily) Definitely.
(Andrew) Yeah, yep. One thing that we see,
and we've got it noted up there on the slides, is raising finance early with cashflow forecasting.
And see, a lot of businesses that come to us and haven't done adequate planning,
and are looking to raise finance when it's often too late.
So, that cashflow forecasting and regular forecasting is so important.
Often it's too late by the time you realize
that you're in a cashflow.. a bit of cashflow difficulty, it's too late to be going to the bank and asking for more money.
(Emily) Yep, I'll totally agree, I think that initially as a small business owner it's probably not everybody's skillset,
is managing finance. So it's something that you'll want to put off, and then you realise how much it impacts on everything that you're doing
but you need to focus on this, this is really important, and I hear from lots of business owners that this is one of the
key reasons that businesses fail, is a lack of cashflow management, so definitely forecast and be prepared
and not bury your head in the sand, pretending that things will get better, is paramount.
(Andrew) Absolutely, having the right information...
(Cara) I've got one question for the two of you already that's coming from Jan.
Jan wants to know what's the difference between a budget and a forecast.
(Andrew) That's a good question, Jan.
For me, and if I'll answer it, let me go first on this.
For me, a budget is something that we would see a business doing it, at the start of the year,
and really setting the goals for maybe the next 12 months or maybe even as far out as
maybe 3 years and using it as a tool to track the performance of the business.
That's setting yourself a good 12-month goal.
A forecast, we would say, is something you update more reguarly.
So, we would encourage our clients to do a budget, probably sometime between now and June.
So, they've got a clear picture of where they want the business to be
over the next 12 months and then update that on a regular basis.
And to forecast out where you're actually going to be, as things evolve.
And certainly cashflow forecasting is something quite different
and that's something that we would encourage clients to
setup a weekly tool that sort of shows, what's coming in this week,
what's going out, and try to forecast that out as far as possible.
And have receipts and expenses which will show any cashflow hole,
or a spot of difficulty, may be three, four, or six months down the track and really use it
as an early warning tool for cashflow difficulty.
(Emily) Yeah and I would say that, my business partner and I, meet weekly to talk about cashflow and
that's something that we've just established in the business. Every week we sit down and talk about,
"Okay, let's look at our cashflow", "Are there going to be any problems?"
"What's coming in; let's look at what's going out." Just to keep the focus on it and so that we're both
really aware of where we're at. Otherwise it's not front of mind and that's when things get out of control.
(Andrew) Yeah. Growing businesses, really, they need cash.
So, that cashflow forecasting as opposed to an annual budget, is really important. So, just moving on to...
(Cara) Okay, sorry before you move on there,
just Emily, people are still having trouble hearing you.
So, if it's possible to speak more directly into the microphone.
And I do have another question,
which is from Hannah, who says, "We have suppliers who use Xerox,
but they're mainly sole traders. Is it good for larger businesses?"
Hannah's currently using a spreadsheet
which shows 1200 customers and she wants to know, would Xerox support that?
(Emily) Yes, definitely.
(Andrew) Yeah. So, Hannah, great work on being able to
manage a business of that size on a spreadsheet, I think that's fantastic.
But, I think it is time to move to a automated system, Xerox,
it's got a really good capability and
we have a number of clients on it, I mean Em's, your business is not a one-man show.
(Emily) No.
(Andrew) So, I think there are some limitations
with the number of employees that can be on the base versions,
but there's a whole lot of pluggins for payroll and stock management and project management,
I'm a big rep for Xerox, I've got a lot of clients on it, my wife's business uses it, and what's your experience been with it Em?
(Emily) I think that the best thing about Xerox is that you don't have to do be an accountant to use this, it's very user friendly.
It's web based, so it's not like you need to buy software and can really get it updated, it's really quite easy to use.
You don't really that much training once it's all set up.
It just kind of runs itself.
(Andrew) Yes, definitely. Very intuitive and very easy to use.
(Emily) Yes.
(Andrew) MYOB, Quickbooks, Saasu, they're all good products.
This is not an advertisement for Xerox,
I guess for all of you lovers of MYOB and quickbooks out there,
but certainly we both find it, very easy to use and it's automation is fantastic and saves a lot of time
and manual entry. So, moving on now.
So, our top three issues that Em and I have come up with, for avoiding cashflow mistakes.
Robust debtor management process, it's so important isn't it?
(Emily) Yep definitely.
(Andrew) And we'll talk more in detail about some examples of good process
and give you some examples about how to deal with problem, problem payers.
That cashflow planning and forecasting,
we keep talking about that over and over and up to date financial information.
It's no good waiting until September, October, or December,
after year end, when you get your tax return or your accounts from your accountant
to look to see how your business has been performing.
That real-time information is absolutely critical.
Cashflow, it's the outcome of the actions and the activities that happen in your business.
So, we're actually in business to make money.
So, the output of that is ultimately cash in the bank
and if we're not monitoring the activities and the actions that we take in our business on a regular basis,
then you're going to end up with cashflow problems, unless you're really lucky.
(Emily) And I'll totally agree with that because unless you make a commitment to manage it,
you overspend and you always think that you've got more money in the bank than you really do.
(Cara) Okay, just another question on that front.
We've got a question from Rob McQueeny.
And he says, "How can you protect yourself against bad debts,
bad debt insurance is a percentage of the insured amount, as our margins are quite small and typically less than 18%"
(Andrew) Yeah. Rob, that's a good question.
So, we've had some clients use debtor insurance before and it is expensive.
That said, certainly one client, it paid for itself when a large debt
that was unpaid and the client went into liquidation.
Other ways that you can protect yourself against bad debts
and we talk about this in the coming slides,
is having director's guarantees, making sure your contracts are right,
using the PPSR and really, I guess, being clear on engaging, how you engage with clients up front.
It's probably time move onto this next section
because this is where we talk about how to prevent customers from becoming late payers.
And this is really also how you protect yourself from your debts.
So, look I think debtor insurance, there's a place for it.
It's not necessarily for all businesses.
If you're looking at using a factoring facility or debtor finance,
then they certainly may require you to use debtor insurance,
but I think there's some simple things that you can put in place, which we'll talk through in the next little while
to help to protect you against, against bad debts.
So, in our tips for preventing customers becoming late payers
and even to follow on from Rob's question, becoming bad debts,
are really things are on agreeing on your trading terms, signing off on your engagement letter, or
agreeing on a scope that works upfront, and choosing your customers really carefully,
that's a critical one and we'll probably go into a bit more detail about that,
asking for a deposit, invoicing regularly; now we see clients that complain that they've
been unable to collect the debt and they've issued the invoice 3 or 4 months
after the service was delivered, it's no wonder the client doesn't want to pay - sending an invoice out,
90 days after the service is sort of indicating that it's not that important that you get paid.
Credit checks and getting on issues early, and on the back of that, monitoring balances regularly.
And so, what's your experience been Em, with signing off on engagements and
and agreeing engagements with clients up front.
(Emily) Yep, that was something I had to learn because initially, we'd just go into the arrangement,
without an engagement letter but
now before we start any engagement, because we're a service based business,
it's really important to get that letter signed off.
And we normally ask for 50% up front and the other 50% when the work is complete,
so that definitely has helped us manage our cashflow.
We invoice regularly so we invoice at the end of the month.
We used to just invoice whenever, but now we've got some rigour in that we
we do it religiously at the end of the month.
And everybody knows that on the first of the next month,
they're going to get their invoice.
So, that's really helped us.
We have seven days payment terms and we get people to sign off on that
and the engagement letter and agree to our terms so find out how they're paying, so those things have really helped us manage our cashflow.
(Andrew) So, on the deposit,
asking for a 50% deposit, how do customer's react to that?
(Emily) It's amazing, most people say "yes, no problem."
There are some people who, who try and get around it.
But they're not really the types of customers that we want.
A lot of the times there will be work involved in setting things up,
we have to go out and buy things to do the job so we need the money up front and we just explain that to them
and they're generally very happy to pay 50% up front, but if they're not, I would advise to leave those one as
they will be the ones who don't want to pay when they get their invoice anyway.
(Andrew) So, choosing your customers carefully is a tip we've got up there to preventing customers
from becoming late payers, so, what experience have you had in,
have you always done that or did you learn the hard way?
(Emily) No, I definitely learnt the hard way.
Initially you accept any business, because you want the business,
and then, now I can see alarm bells going off, if I see them going off I just won't work with that customer,
so it really is about picking your customers carefully and I was giving Andrew an example before
where I had a client that was a serial late payer, and now I don't do business with them any more because it just wasn't worth it.
(Andrew) Yeah. It's really,
it sounds like its really about having confidence in your own ability, in your own service and the product.
(Emily) Definitely.
(Andrew) And having the ability to say no to potential business can be difficult.
(Emily) Yeah.
(Andrew) But, it can prevent a lot of issues down the track.
(Emily) Yeah, well, I totally agree with that.
(Cara) Okay, I've got another question for you.
It's come from Sharon.
She's a sole trader and wants to know should she have an engagement letter put together
and is that something she can write herself or does it need to be a legal document?
(Andrew) That's a good question, Cara.
And the, I think the answer probably varies.
I think it probably depends on, you know, the type of work she's doing, the nature of it,
how much money is involved.
If they're, if they're big contracts and big engagements,
I would think then that's probably worth getting some legal advice around it.
But, if they're smaller engagements,
then perhaps it's something that she could even draw up
together with her customers and clients,
to say, well, these are the terms of the engagements
and this is what we're going to the deliver and this is what we expect from you.
Em, what have you done with your engagement letters?
(Emily) I actually used an engagement
letter that somebody had given me, one of my service providers,
and I just changed it and adapted it so that I could use it for myself.
So, it's not a legal document, I'm a service based business so it's a little bit different, I imagine if you were
a stock based business, it would probably need to be a little bit more in depth and complicated.
So don't be afraid to plagiarise and steal hints from other people and make them your own, is my advice.
(Andrew) Yeah. In small business,
I think, that we've got to take a practical approach.
I would say, Cara, our advice to Sharon would be,
depending on the size of the, and nature of engagement,
if they're complicated and there are large dollars involved,
then it's certainly worth getting then getting some legal advice,
but if they're, they're smaller contracts,
I think, she could probably talk to them and maybe even draft things up
with her customers so that they do them together.
And take Em's advice and see if she can't find
engagement letter from, maybe even a service provider that you use Sharon.
(Emily) And Sharon, Google is always great.
Just type it in and you'll be amazed at what you can find online.
There's hundreds of free templates available- so that's another option.
(Cara) Okay.
We've got another question, which is possibly airing on the side of legal advice, as well.
But, this is from Amanda and she works in the Child Care industry.
And she said they've had a parent who signed all the contracts and agreements,
and now refuses to pay as he said English is not his first language
and he never understood what he was signing.
(Emily) Okay.
(Andrew) Yeah. I think, I think there's certainly, there's time when you've got to get advice
and you have to get the right advice.
And we can't give legal advice out here today.
Cara, I don't know.
You're not asking us to, but I think that's probably, that's probably the next step for Amanda,
depending on, you know, the amount of dollars involved.
The other thing she could do is refer it to a debt collection- a debt collector
or debt collection agency as well.
So...
(Cara) Okay, great.
And I'll let you keep on moving before I ask some more questions.
(Andrew) No worries.
And so, if we move on, Em, our top three tips for preventing late payers,
choosing your customers carefully and that takes confidence, doesn't it?
You've got to have faith in your own ability, your own product and service to say no to potential business.
(Emily) Yeah. Definitely.
(Andrew) Agree your trading terms and your scope, in writing.
Now, that's..
so many disputes can be avoided by having it in writing up front before you commence.
(Emily) Yeah.
That's something that I definitely learnt the hard way.
it's about having everything in writing, people revert to their own rules and generally, they're not in your favour.
(Andrew) Definitely.
So, agree it in writing and finally,
follow your debtor management process religiously.
If you're gonna have a process, well there's no point having a process
if you're not going to follow it.
(Emily) And, you know, as a business owner this is not fun,
and it's not something that I love doing but I've learned that I have to do it
because it's one of the most important things that you need to do day to day.
(Andrew) Yeah. Having a process no doubt, it helps that.
And so, looking at ways to deal with late paying customers.
Again, there's a whole range of different things that we can do.
These are the things that we thought were the most critical when it comes to
so, if we haven't been able educate them, and coach the customers and train them
by using those tips and techniques that we spoke of earlier, here are some ways that we can deal with late paying customers.
You've got to have a debtor system.
If you don't have a debtor system, you've got no real way of tracking them and having a follow up process,
so it's amazing how quickly 90 days can fly, if you're not looking at your debtors and chasing payments.
Value your product and service, following the system,
keep in close contact with your customers.
I mean, everyone has a right to be paid.
I think, if you value your product or service and remember that people
want to buy it, and usually they're, you know, if you do have debtors,
you're in the trade and dealing with other businesses who are either
on-selling or in business themselves, they're looking to make money too.
So, everyone has a right to be paid.
And don't be afraid to ask for payment, we'll talk about that one in a sec.
Get advice, use debt collectors, and train your staff
in your processes, don't feel like you have to leave it up to yourself and asking customers to commit to an amount
and date, and maybe using payment arrangements, if customers are having difficulty paying at that time.
So, what's your experience, Em, in dealing with late payers?
(Emily) My experience is that if you keep on top of it,
normally the person who is shouting the loudest will be the first to be paid.
So, if you're not shouting, you will get pushed to the bottom of the queue, and I've learnt that.
So, it's about emailing, communicating,
following it up with a phone call, and then if you get no response making sure that you send
a formal letter of demand and that seems to work extremely well.
But, you need to be on top of it.
You need to make sure that you're polite.
If you're rude or forceful, they're not gonna respond very nicely to you.
So, it's just about making sure that you follow your process, that you're courteous, build a relationship with
the accounts payable person, learn who you need to be speaking to because often that will help you get the result you want.
(Andrew) So, do you like chasing debtors?
(Emily) Definitely not. It's not fun. But I learnt the hard way that I have to do it.
So, I'm now very disciplined about making sure that I chase debtors,
and initially it was probably very scary, ringing up and asking for money.
But now I've done it a lot of times, you definitely get more comfortable and confident asking for money.
(Andrew) Yeah.
If you want to be in small business, it's just it's one of those jobs that no one likes doing.
And unfortunately, you can't be in business without collecting your debtors.
(Emily)That's right.
(Cara) So, I've got a question on that topic from Tammy.
She says their business involves trade, she's a trades person,
so, most transactions are under $200.
So, what would be a good way to inform lots of smaller customers of your
payment terms without putting them off your services?
(Andrew) Yeah, so, I think, my sense is, and Em and I have spoken about this quite a bit today already,
you need to value your products and services, Tammy,
And you need to just have confidence that people want to buy them.
The other thing that might be, if you're worried that some people might leave
or stop using your business,
is, have a think about how much time you spend chasing debtors
and chasing money and try to quantify that.
And then think about how much business you could afford to lose
before you're actually going backwards.
The transactions under $200, I would even think about looking at
taking credit card payments at time of delivery or COD, or something like that.
I think these days where there's low dollar amounts, where transactions are low dollar amounts,
people are more and more used to paying up front,
and paying for things not on credit,
you can go to the doctor, it'll cost you $60 or $70,
you're not allowed to put that on a 30 or a 60 day account.
You go to the petrol station and fill your car up,
that costs you a hundred bucks, you've got to pay it at that time.
Your phone bill, yeah, look I'm sure everyone forgets to pay the bill,
but we all know that pretty quickly after that the due date the phone companies will stop outgoing calls.
So, I think customers, generally, particularly with smaller amounts,
are used to having to pay that quickly, so I think
it comes down to having the confidence, changing the trading terms
communicate it openly and that could be by letter or e-mail,
or if you've got some customers that spend a lot with you
and you could certainly get on the phone or go and see them.
Communicate it openly, communicate why you're doing it and have some confidence in your product and service.
(Emily) And you can always buy one of those EFT machines
that are wireless now. You can take that wherever you go so you're making people pay on that at the
end of the job and doesn't give you an option.
(Andrew) Yep, Yep, that's a great idea.
A wireless credit card machine,
and back to the earlier comments, I think people expect to pay at the time of service,
particularly for those smaller trades jobs.
(Cara) We've got a question from James.
Who wants to know, what's the difference between a Letter of Agreement and your terms?
(Andrew) So I would say a Letter of Agreement, I think that James is probably
talking about an Engagement Letter, and the scope, to say, these are the things we're going to do.
You know if you're a service business, this is what we're going to do
over what time frame and this is what you're going to do to help
deliver that service as a customer or a client, and these are the things we're going to do and these are the outcomes.
If you're a trade or a whole sale or stock related business, this would be the
things that we're going to deliver to you in what time frames and whatnot,
so your commitments around the service, whereas your terms of trade are,
we expect, you know 50% deposit and the balance 30 days from end of month, or seven days from invoice or whatnot.
So I think there's certainly the engagement letter or how you do business and then your trading terms of how you expect to be paid.
(Emily) Yep, my letter of engagement, actually includes the trading terms in it, because it's not a stock or wholesale business,
so trading terms I think it would be more relevant for a bigger business in dealing with stock, but I think that it can include both.
(Cara) Okay, one more question on this topic,
how do you get around the fact that, -it's from Simone,
and she wants to know how do you get around
the fact you're trading terms may be 14 days but the customer your dealing with
says they only pay at the end of the following month?
This does tend to be larger companies.
I know from our readers, this is a real issue where, if you're a smaller business dealing with a larger business,
you may not have that much negotiating power.
(Emily) Yeah and I've had that issue before,
and I guess you need to make the call about whether
you can afford to service that client because I work with clients
and they make me sign up to their trading terms,
they're bigger, and they can boss you around I guess and force you into doing that,
and generally because they are a bigger corporate organisation you kind of have to suck it up.
But I would try and avoid it at all costs.
You know, think of work arounds, think of ways that they might be able to negotiate with you
and explain why you need to do that, but sometimes I guess you have to
make a call and decide if I agree on whether to do that.
(Andrew) Yeah, I'd agree with Em there Cara. Simone, I think it's a decision you make as to
who do you want to do business with, if you want to do
business with corporates that in-flexible with their trading terms and only pay
60 days or whatever it is, well that's a choice that you have to make, and if you don't want to
do business with them then you back yourself to go and find the customers that
you want to deal with, and for me it comes back to the phone example,
I'd love to pay my phone bill in 90 days but thats,
I've been trained that that doesn't work. Look if you can't train the customer,
not all customers can be trained, I think that's probably fair to say.
And then that becomes a decision as to whether you want to do business with that type of business.
(Cara) Okay. And from Phil, we have a question, is there an example of a debtor management process
which I think leads pretty perfectly onto your next slide.
(Andrew) It sure does, so this is something that Em and I put together as an example
of a debtor recovery process and there's some great templates and tips on the Business Victoria website,
so, to start off, certainly getting the invoice out on time, send that with the goods
or in line with the engagement letter, or the service agreement, don't wait for a month,
send it out as soon as the goods have been delivered, or the services
have been filled or send them out with the engagement letter or service agreement.
Step 2 would be after sending the invoice, and not leaving it too late, is
give your customer a call, make sure that they've got the invoice,
make sure that they've got the goods or services
and that there's no issues, confirm the payment terms and really, this helps to
determine if there's any obstacles to receiving the payment, so it clears the way for the payment.
It can be a customer service call, with a little hint of reminder around the trading terms,
and the conversation might be along the lines of, you know, "Hi Em, you know we've finished your accounts for the year
we sent the invoice out last week, is everything in order, no problems, good. If there's any issues let us know,
we've had a look and we're happy with that, yep make sure its in your system, and remember the payment terms of 30 days.
Can you see any issues with that Em, in terms of not been able to pay that on time?"
So it's just a gently, softly customer service type call that clears the way for any
obstacles for payment. Be proactive about getting issues out on the table,
we certainly see quite often that, that aged debts often come with an issue
either relate to the service or product, so the earlier you can deal with that issue,
the quicker you are going to be able to resolve it and get paid, don't wait for the customer to come to you,
be proactive. Then once the account is sorted, if the account is overdue,
then a follow up call or email or letter, again there are some great templates
on the Business Victoria website, so that's around 7 days before the account is 7 days overdue. Another reminder
something a little more firm, before its 14 days overdue, then once it hits 30 days and no later,
something really firm like a final notice, outlining the consequences, if you don't receive payment by a certain date,
then last day, a formal letter or instructing a solicitor or debt collection agency once your account is more than 30 days
overdue. So that's an example, so the sorts of things that you do, Em, you use a similar process, so how do you find that works?
(Emily) Yeah, so I've got a process, where initially I send a very friendly email if its overdue,
and I know its overdue becasue I am in Xerox everyday to see if people have paid or not,
and then if it's still not paid or I don't get a response, I send another email,
then I would give them a call, and once again and make sure I'm speaking to the right person.
Sometimes the accounts payable person is not the right person to be speaking to, you need to
speak to the person in the company who actually engaged you, and let them know that it's not been paid
and that you need them to sort it out. If you know the business owner, sometimes it's good to copy them in, and
that will get things moving generally, sometimes if they just ignore you, which some people do,
making sure that you send a formal letter of demand, you don't have to use a debt collector, I've never used a debt collector because I can't afford to,
so just saying, if you don't pay by this date, normally I give them 7 days, I'll be instructing my solicitor to take it further
and you will have to pay not only the invoice, but costs as well.
(Andrew) Yep, and what sort of response do you get from that approach once it gets to that stage?
(Emily) Oh, only twice have I ever had to give the formal letter of demand, generally it gets paid before that,
it generally works, because as I said before, the person who screams the loudest, will get paid, and I think that's a good common sense approach.
(Andrew) Yeah, and relationships- like do you find that, I know often, businesses worry about damaging relationships
they have with their customers and clients by asking for payments and issuing demands and those sorts of things,
so how does that - what's your experience with that?
(Emily) It's never impacted on a relationship, because I think it's about mutual respect
because if I do a good job, and I provide a really good service then I should be allowed to get paid for it.
And, also I'm always extremely courteous, friendly, never rude, I never raise my voice or get angry,
although I feel like it sometimes obviously, it's just about being really respectful.
(Andrew) Yeah, I think the other thing is when you're on the phone, if you are speaking to someone, be prepared
to take a payment, or ask for a payment, then and there.
(Emily) Exactly right, "So when can I expect payment, can you pay today?"
If they say no I can't pay today, you say, when can you make the payment?" if they say tomorrow, then you check the next day to see
if it's gone in, because a lot of the time people will say yes they will pay it, but then they don't
and if you just let it just run out even more time will lapse, so it's really about following up
and having the discipline to follow up, not being afraid to ask for even a half payment,
so if you can't make the whole payment, can you pay half, and then when can I expect the rest?
(Andrew) Yeah so setting up a payment plan can sometimes make it easier for the customer
and having some cash, is surely better than having none and waiting another month, or 6 weeks.
(Emily) Yes.
(Cara) We've got a tip as well, from one of our participants, Hayden who says
one of the best ways he's found, is to ask the recalcitrant payer to ask if the're trading whilst insolvent,
you then, say that you wouldn't want to refer them to Asic and surely they can find a way to pay your invoice. Usually it works.
So that's a bit of a creative approach, but I like that.
We've also got, a question from Paul, who is in the construction industry, and he says
they're in line with the building and construction industry security of payment act,
which entitles them to charge interest as per section 101 of the civil procedure act, which is approximately 9%
for all overdue payments. And Paul wants to know if either of you have had any experience applying this?
And if so, how did you do it successfully so that the client paid the principle and the interest?
Now Emily, given that you're in HR, I doubt that you've had experience under the building and construction industry act,
but perhaps this is something you have come across Andrew?
(Andrew) Yeah, so generally Cara, and Paul, that's a good question,
we've certainly had experience in charging interest and it certainly is not uncommon to build it into your
terms and conditions as well, so there's nothing to stop you from, as long as you're disclosing it
to your clients and customers that it's your intention that your going charge interest on
overdue accounts at a certain rate, if they sign off on those terms and conditions,
then they've agreed to the fact that they can be charged interest. So it's another thing
to get paid interest, which I think is probably Paul's question,
my sense is that its probably more of a stick than it is a money making scheme, in terms of
using the interest to make some money. So it's not uncommon to, we certainly see clients
that charge interest, they might put it on their statements and whatnot, but when a client
pays within a certain period of time, they'll remit the interest or remove the interest,
or use that as a lever to get payment sooner rather than later, so I think that's probably
what we've seen, is that, you can use it as a leverage to get payment sooner if there's an interest accruing on it.
The other thing is that if it does turn nasty, and end up in legal action,
if you've been charging interest, it makes it much easier to ask the courts to award the interest.
So that's certainly something that we've seen from our experience.
That could apply to Paul's situation in the construction game.
(Cara) Okay great, thanks for that.
(Andrew) So, have you got any other questions Cara, or we'll play on?
(Cara) I'll let you move onto your next slide, and then we've got a few more, but keep moving along and I can ask the next lot.
(Andrew) So, really there, Em, we've got our top tips for dealing with late payers, developing a process, train your customers, so,
it's amazing how quickly customers will learn that they've got to pay you within your trade terms
otherwise they're going to get bombarded with phone calls and emails that take up their time, it's easier
just to pay squeaky wheel, rather than hear it carry on month after month, so training your customers
is really important and that can take time. Training your staff, so making sure that people are prepared
to receive a payment, there's nothing worse than if you've been chasing a debt, and a client calls and you're out of the office
and you end up playing phone tag, so, train your team to be ready to accept payment, always have your credit card machine,
or your bank details handy- whatever it is, how you best receive payments, train your staff
in this process too. Particularly, if you're no good at this or really don't like it
then you've got to find someone in your organisation, who can do it, and is prepared to do it,
so train them accordingly.
Understanding your customers payment cycles, so that goes back to, if your customers all pay 60 days, and you're
14 days, then you're in the wrong place, and you need to think long and hard about whether you want to continue to work for those type
of customers or whether you change your business.
Accurate and detailed records - how can you know what's overdue, if you haven't got good invoicing
a good automated debtor management system, like Xerox or MYOB or something like that.
So having accurate and detailed records, it's no good reconciling once a quarter,
you've got to do it weekly, I think it's an absolute must, that you do it weekly.
Follow up regularly, that squeaky wheel that we were talking about before, that's how the world works.
So just some comments around training your staff, what's your experience been in that?
(Emily) Well I had to train myself, so it was a process of me learning how to do it,
making it a priority, and I've said it a couple of times, being disciplined,
because it's not something that I like doing, but I have to force myself to do it,
and I think that's every small business owners biggest challenge,
is that it's not my area of expertise, I'm not a finance person and I've had to become good at things that I've never been good at before.
Which is challenging, but it's rewarding when it all comes together.
(Andrew) Yeah, and if you're a growing business, cash is the life float of your business,
so like it or not, you've got to deal with cashflow proactively, you've got to
deal with debtor management proactively, otherwise you may not be in business very long.
So all businesses out there that are listening, that are in a bit of growth phase,
it's absolutely paramount that, if you don't have good record keeping system, a good debtor management process,
that cashflow will continue to be, the bane of your life.
And we know, its the number one issue for our clients.
So just, the last slide there is...
(Cara) Just before we, sorry I was going to interrupt but I may as well let you give your
top three tips for today and then we'll go through the rest of the questions.
(Andrew) No worries. So, we've been banging on about it Em, but good accurate records,
up to date records, it's an absolute must. Choosing your customers carefully,
engage with them proactively, upfront, and train them,
and having a good debtor system and discipline,
and as a small business owner, no doubt you find that you've got plenty of excuses as to why
you shouldn't pick up the phone or send that email to chase the debtors,
but you've got to have that discipline to follow the process.
(Emily) Yep, I totally agree, it's not fun, but it's part of my day to day operations now.
(Andrew) Yeah, a big part of business. So, there's some great tips and advice on the Business Victoria website,
with how to manage cashflow and deal with getting paid on time. So some great tips
and templates and whatnot.
(Emily) And scripts as well, about what to say, because I think that's quite scary to some people,
is how do I do this, how do I have a conversation I don't want to damage my relationship - there's some
great scripts on there to show you how to do it.
(Andrew) Fantastic. So head to the Business website. So Cara, some more questions?
(Cara) Yes we definitely have quite a few more questions and thanks everyone for the great
questions you've been sending through. A few questions on the topic of interest, so
Sonia says, she's found that what works is when she puts on her invoices that she charges 2.5%
so that's a good tip from Sonia, but we've got a question from James,
who wants to know, what would a reasonable interest amount be, to charge clients on their outstanding balances?
(Andrew) Oh, James it's really what you think is reasonable. So I mean, we've certainly seen it, a recent example there was 2.5%
and we've seen it as high as 18 - 19%, so pick something you're comfortable with,
if it's too low people might see it as cheap finance, so you're not in the business of financing your customers,
so I think it's got to be high enough so that it's a stick and a disincentive for people to hold you out.
The flipside of that, which we haven't talked about, is early payment incentives and discounts
so that's another stick on one side being interest, and an early payment discount on the other side,
is another good way.
(Cara) Okay, and I guess actually leading right onto that, Kerry Anne wants to know
is it reasonable to ask for a 50% upfront payment?
(Emily) Yeah, definitely, that's what I do in my business, is I ask for 50% up front and the other
50% when the job is completed. And I think that is more than reasonable.
(Andrew) Yeah, I think you've just got to know your market.
Some people will be able to charge upfront, everything, some people might only accept 30%.
And you might train your customers that where the industry has a 10% deposit, you might train them to be 50%.
So I think it depends on your business and your market, but as Em has experienced,
50% in her game, works.
(Cara) So Martin suggests charging, what you're paying on your overdraft plus an overhead for admin.
That's how he works it out.
(Andrew) Great formula Martin, great formula.
(Cara) He'd make sure he's not out of pocket there. And Sonia has a tip as well, she says on the topic
of training customers, she's changed her statements so they read 'current and overdue' rather than
'current 30, 60 and 90,' so it's really taking out that next step or possiblity.
(Andrew) Yep, it's also, great, great thinking there.
(Cara) So in the debtor management process slide, we've just got a question about that from Frank,
and he says, at which step do you say, no further supplies or services until payment of the outstanding debt is made.
When would you put your foot down, to that extent?
(Emily) Well that's a good question, I guess it's case by case, it depends on how much
they've got outstanding, I have definitely put people on hold that I know I'm not doing anymore
business with you until you pay your account. I think that when it gets to a point
when its over 30 days overdue, that that's when I would say no more.
(Andrew) Yeah and I think that that's a pretty good place to start. If they're your
largest customer and you can see a way forward and they're communicating with you openly
and they're making some payments and you feel confident that their cashflow issues
are short term, then you might decide to ride it out with them.
But if you can't see a way forward, then I think the earlier you stop supply, the better.
(Cara) Yep, okay, we've got a question from Cameron and he wants to know
what you do in the situation where an administrator or receiver is appointed,
if you're a unsecured creditor, what are your obligations to support the company under administration?
(Andrew) Yeah, that's a really good question Cameron, so it probably depends on how much you're owed,
so if you're owed a lot of money and it's going to cause you severe difficulties then I would be
very proactive with the administrator in terms of doing what you can to help through.
If you're owed a small amount, then and you can afford to write it off or whatnot,
I think you probably, history would say, those smaller creditors unsecured don't get paid
in those circumstances, it's very unlikely and you can spend a lot of time and effort
chasing a small payment when that time and effort could be spent chasing new business or better servicing your
good customers who pay on time. So I think it's a question as to what impact is it going to have
on your business and how much time is it going to take to chase down a payment,
and the trade off - where else could that time be better spent?
(Cara) Okay great, thanks Andrew. I've got a question from Johnno, he runs a computer repair business
in regional Victoria and he said he's got a couple of customers which he didn't have a
written agreement with, can he still go through the recovery process?
(Andrew) Yeah, I think even without a written agreement, there's no reason why
if you've supplied a product or services, and you've got evidence of that,
there's no reason why you can't chase the debt, and there's also no reason why if you haven't had a written
agreement with a customer, you can't put one in for future activities, just becuase you've been dealing with
someone for the last 5 years on a handshake, doesn't mean you can't go to them and say, look,
we've been doing this on a handshake, let's formalise this a bit because it will be good for you,
and it will be good for us.
(Emily) I think that a letter of demand, normally gets people moving, or else not
from a solicitor, they go, oh okay this is getting serious now, so it's a formal message
that looks a little bit scarier than just the normal email or phone call.
So I would advise that, that would be step one.
And then if that doesn't work, then actually going and finding a solicitor who's going
to send them a letter, because there's nothing like a solicitors letterhead to scare people.
(Cara) Okay. Brian wants to know has sending those letters of demand lost you any customers?
(Emily) No, never.
(Cara) That's good to hear, the process does work. A few final tips from our listeners.
We've got Marie-Claire, she only asks for 50% deposits from big companies that might be able to get around the
14 day trading terms, so that's one suggestion. And another one from Andra, who says
she charges a $25 statement fee for all accounts over 30 days. And that scares
a lot of people into paying. So they're both good tips there.
But we should finish things up there, because we are coming up to the end of our hour,
so I know that all of you listening have got businesses to run and things to do,
and so do our presenters, so I would really like to thank our two presenters,
who have really been so generous with their time and expertise today, Andrew and Emily,
we've really appreciated that, and special thanks to our partner for today's webinar Business Victoria.
As you've heard during the seminar, their website is really a wealth of information
for all of this sort of information, so it's a really good resource to go to,
www.business.vic.gov.au and it's got templates on there and tips.
So thank you very much everyone for your time and stay tuned for the next
Smart Company webinar, there's another one coming up in the next week or so.
Thanks Emily and Andrew.
(Emily)Thank you. (Andrew) Thanks Cara.